<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ravioli1369.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ravioli1369.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-11-10T01:06:20+05:30</updated><id>https://ravioli1369.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">faintest of the brightest: grb hunters</title><link href="https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2023/grb-hunters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="faintest of the brightest: grb hunters"/><published>2023-07-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2023/grb-hunters</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2023/grb-hunters/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/science/objects/bursts1.html">gamma-ray bursts</a> (GRBs) are fascinating astronomical phenomena that have captured the attention of scientists and researchers around the world. these powerful bursts of gamma-ray radiation, lasting from a fraction of a second to a few minutes, provide valuable insights into the universe’s workings.</p> <p>the grb hunters project aims to create a method to detect grbs based on their signal-to-noise ratio in the data from the Cadmium Zinc Telluride Imager (CZTI) onboard ISRO’s AstroSat.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="grb"/><category term="astronomy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a blog post detailing the grb hunters project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the basics</title><link href="https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2022/the-basics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the basics"/><published>2022-10-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2022/the-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2022/the-basics/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="playing-with-light"><strong>Playing with light</strong></h1> <p>There are <strong>three</strong> main ways of controlling the amount and quality of light that a sensor recieves. One being the aperture, another being the shutter speed and lastly we have the ISO. There’s a couple neat little analogies we can use to understand these three qualities.</p> <p>Think about filling an ice cube tray under a tap with running water. In our analogy the running water serves the purpose of light, and the cubes in the tray represent the pixels on a sensor.</p> <h2 id="aperture"><strong>Aperture</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/aperture-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/aperture-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/aperture-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/aperture.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The <strong>aperture</strong> determines exactly how much light is let in through the lens, in the case of our analogy, the aperture would be the diameter of the tap that supplies the water, the larger the diameter, the more the amount of water (light) that can enter the tray (sensor).</p> <p>On a camera, the aperture is usually measured as a ratio between the focal length and the diameter of the opening in the lens, known as the <strong>f-number</strong> or <strong>f-stop</strong>. This approach is used as the size of the opening relative to the focal length is what determines the amount of light that is collected. For example, two lenses of different focal lengths but the same apertures will collect the same amount of light but at very different fields of view.</p> <p>The <strong>focal length</strong> of a lens basically determines how wide of a field of view the camera can see, a lower focal length allows us to capture more of the surroundings in frame, and a higher focal length narrows down our field of view and puts the focus on a single object. Higher focal lengths are used generally for portraits, far away objects like the moon, etc.</p> <p>Say a lens has a focal length of 50mm and the diameter of its opening is 25mm, then its f-number will be 50 divided by 25 which is equal to 2. We denote this by adding an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f</code> in front of the ratio: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f2.0</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f/2.0</code>. The smaller the f-number, the larger is the opening on the lens. It is a bit counterintuitive and there’s no real way of justifying why it is the way it is aside from just convention.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bokeh-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bokeh-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bokeh-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/bokeh.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Ever wondered how or why some photos have a very blurred background with circular-looking blobs of light? Well, that has to do with something called <strong>depth of field</strong> or <strong>bokeh</strong>, which determines how much of the background is out of focus. Good quality bokeh is a favorite amongst photographers and videographers alike, it helps isolate the subject and allows cinematographers to pull the <em>focus</em> (pun intended) of the audience from one actor to another.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <iframe width="444" height="250" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_lZvF-YyP0s?si=tR0uuyyE7p6A9iia&amp;start=310" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> Here's a nice video that shows how changes in the aperture affect the depth of field produced by the lens. (The video is meant to start at 5:10, watching till 9:12 should be sufficient). </div> </div> <h3 id="how-to-choose-the-correct-aperture"><strong>How to choose the correct aperture?</strong></h3> <p>The choice of aperture comes down to the nature of what a photographer is trying to capture.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/cat-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/cat-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/cat-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/cat.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/powai_lake-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/powai_lake-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/powai_lake-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/powai_lake.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> A large aperture (small f-number) paired with a large focal length leads to the maximum amount of bokeh. This kind of setup is perfect for portraits where you try and isolate the subject from the busyness of the background.<br/> <br/> This picture of a cat, shot at f/1.8 and 50mm, shows how the cat is in focus but the lights in the background and the background itself are completely out of focus, helping the viewer to focus on the subject. </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> A smaller aperture (larger f-number) along with a smaller focal length produces very little bokeh and keeps most of the frame in focus, this is perfect for landscapes where every part of a vast terrain needs to be in focus.<br/> <br/> This picture of the Powai Lake, shot at f/11 and 50mm, shows how each part of the lake is in focus, helping the viewer to see the picture as a whole rather than to focus on a specific part. </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/fireworks-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/fireworks-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/fireworks-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/fireworks.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>There’s another interesting artifact caused by the aperture of a lens which can be seen in the form of spikes on the point sources of light in this picture of a firework. This effect is also known as the <strong>starburst</strong> effect as it is most prominent while taking pictures of the sun. This shot was taken at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f/16</code> which is a very small opening on the lens.</p> <p>If we look at the picture of the lens at the beginning of the aperture subheading, we can see that the lens has seven “blades” forming a heptagon that open and close to change the size of the iris. Now looking again at the above image we can see that there are fourteen spikes in each point source, this specific number comes from the number of blades a lens has. A lens that has an even number of aperture blades produces the same number of spikes, whereas a lens with an odd number of blades produces double the number of spikes, that’s why we see fourteen spikes using a lens that has seven blades.</p> <h2 id="shutter-speed"><strong>Shutter speed</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/waterdrop-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/waterdrop-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/waterdrop-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/waterdrop.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Next, we have the <strong>shutter speed</strong> also known as <strong>exposure time</strong> of a camera tells us the duration for which the sensor is exposed to light, if we take the example of our analogy, then the shutter speed would be signified by how long the tap is running or a more accurate way of saying it would be the amount of time the tray is under the tap.</p> <p>The usual way of measuring the shutter speed is in terms of fractions of a second (1/100s, 1/50s, 1/320s and so on). Choosing the right shutter speed is very important when it comes to the sharpness of an image. While photographing people or pets, the preferred shutter speed would be faster than 1/100s (here faster than would mean a numerically smaller value than 1/100) so as to minimise motion blur. With a slower shutter speed (longer exposure) theres more motion blur that can be introduced into an image, the motion blur can be from the subject or from the photographer’s hand itself.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <iframe width="444" height="250" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CmjeCchGRQo?si=976aDkaigSkdDyz9" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> Here's a good video that shows how the shutter of a camera actually works. </div> </div> <h3 id="how-to-choose-the-correct-shutter-speed"><strong>How to choose the correct shutter speed?</strong></h3> <p>The choice of shutter speed again depends on the look and feel the photographer wants their image to have.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/another_waterdrop-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/another_waterdrop-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/another_waterdrop-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/another_waterdrop.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/welding-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/welding-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/welding-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/welding.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> Sometimes a photographer would want to capture a very sharp image with every little detail frozen in time. For such an effect a faster shutter speed is chosen, usually something faster than 1/1000s, but depends entirely on how fast the subject is.<br/> <br/> This picture of a waterdrop that fell in a tub of water for instance, was shot with an exposure of 1/5000s. Every part of the drop is tack sharp and no motion blur can be seen. </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> Othertimes they would want an intentional blur to signify the movement of an object. It's an interesting way of showing that an object is moving in a photograph rather than a video. Anything from 1/10s to multiple seconds would work.<br/> <br/> Here is a picture of a man welding, shot with an exposure of 5s shows trails of hot molten metal falling off of the weld. We can also see the movement of the arm on the right side of the image. </div> </div> <h2 id="iso"><strong>ISO</strong></h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/sanat-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/sanat-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/sanat-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/sanat.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Finally we come to the <strong>ISO</strong> of a sensor. ISO stands for International Organisation of Standards, which basically means nothing without a backstory. Back in the days of film photography, the sensitivity of the film (the amount of silver salts present in the sheet of film) would act as a third way of increasing or decreasing the amount of “light” in a photo. The term light is used handwavily here as no extra light is falling on the film itself, rather a higher ISO film is just more sensitive to the already present light, in other words, this is “artificial light”.</p> <p>With higher ISOs, there comes a trade off in the image quality. A higher ISO requires more silver salts in the film roll which creates a “grain” that can be seen in the final result. This grain is seen as small dots (kind of like pepper flakes) all over the image. We can see such a result in the above image, especially along the right side.</p> <p>In digital photography, the ISO represents the sensitivity of the sensor itself to light. This sensitivity is changed electronically through amplifiers, i.e. the voltage itself is amplified to give the perception of more light. All this amplification leads to what we call “noise” for a digital camera. This noise is basically pixels that are either too sensitive to the light or not sensitive enough, and is mainly caused because of very minute imperfections in the manufacturing process.</p> <h3 id="how-to-choose-the-correct-iso"><strong>How to choose the correct ISO?</strong></h3> <p>When it comes to ISO, there isnt really an artistic reason to choose ISOs like there was with shutter speed or aperture. Once a photographer is satisfied with their choice of shutter speed and aperture, they then move onto the ISO and adjust it till they are happy with their exposure. Usually we try and stay at the lowest possible ISO that gives a perfectly exposed image so as to reduce noise. However, grain can be added back into the photo during post processing (editing) to achieve a filmic look which is quite a popular look and feel nowadays.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="photography"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[learn the absolute basics of photography - light and its interactions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a distill-style blog post</title><link href="https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2021/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a distill-style blog post"/><published>2021-05-22T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-05-22T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2021/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ravioli1369.github.io/blog/2021/distill/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="equations">Equations</h2> <p>This theme supports rendering beautiful math in inline and display modes using <a href="https://www.mathjax.org/">MathJax 3</a> engine. You just need to surround your math expression with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code>, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$ E = mc^2 $$</code>. If you leave it inside a paragraph, it will produce an inline expression, just like \(E = mc^2\).</p> <p>To use display mode, again surround your expression with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code> and place it as a separate paragraph. Here is an example:</p> \[\left( \sum_{k=1}^n a_k b_k \right)^2 \leq \left( \sum_{k=1}^n a_k^2 \right) \left( \sum_{k=1}^n b_k^2 \right)\] <p>Note that MathJax 3 is <a href="https://docs.mathjax.org/en/latest/upgrading/whats-new-3.0.html">a major re-write of MathJax</a> that brought a significant improvement to the loading and rendering speed, which is now <a href="http://www.intmath.com/cg5/katex-mathjax-comparison.php">on par with KaTeX</a>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="citations">Citations</h2> <p>Citations are then used in the article body with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-cite&gt;</code> tag. The key attribute is a reference to the id provided in the bibliography. The key attribute can take multiple ids, separated by commas.</p> <p>The citation is presented inline like this: <d-cite key="gregor2015draw"></d-cite> (a number that displays more information on hover). If you have an appendix, a bibliography is automatically created and populated in it.</p> <p>Distill chose a numerical inline citation style to improve readability of citation dense articles and because many of the benefits of longer citations are obviated by displaying more information on hover. However, we consider it good style to mention author last names if you discuss something at length and it fits into the flow well — the authors are human and it’s nice for them to have the community associate them with their work.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2> <p>Just wrap the text you would like to show up in a footnote in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-footnote&gt;</code> tag. The number of the footnote will be automatically generated.<d-footnote>This will become a hoverable footnote.</d-footnote></p> <hr/> <h2 id="code-blocks">Code Blocks</h2> <p>Syntax highlighting is provided within <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-code&gt;</code> tags. An example of inline code snippets: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-code language="html"&gt;let x = 10;&lt;/d-code&gt;</code>. For larger blocks of code, add a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">block</code> attribute:</p> <d-code block="" language="javascript"> var x = 25; function(x) { return x * x; } </d-code> <p><strong>Note:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;d-code&gt;</code> blocks do not look good in the dark mode. You can always use the default code-highlight using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">highlight</code> liquid tag:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">25</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">x</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="nx">x</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure> <hr/> <h2 id="interactive-plots">Interactive Plots</h2> <p>You can add interative plots using plotly + iframes :framed_picture:</p> <div class="l-page"> <iframe src="/assets/plotly/demo.html" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" height="500px" width="100%" style="border: 1px dashed grey;"></iframe> </div> <p>The plot must be generated separately and saved into an HTML file. To generate the plot that you see above, you can use the following code snippet:</p> <figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">pandas</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">pd</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">plotly.express</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">px</span>
<span class="n">df</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">pd</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">read_csv</span><span class="p">(</span>
  <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/plotly/datasets/master/earthquakes-23k.csv</span><span class="sh">'</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">px</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">density_mapbox</span><span class="p">(</span>
  <span class="n">df</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">lat</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Latitude</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">lon</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Longitude</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">z</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">Magnitude</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">radius</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">center</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nf">dict</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">lat</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lon</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">180</span><span class="p">),</span>
  <span class="n">zoom</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">mapbox_style</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">stamen-terrain</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">fig</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">show</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">fig</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">write_html</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">assets/plotly/demo.html</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span></code></pre></figure> <hr/> <h2 id="details-boxes">Details boxes</h2> <p>Details boxes are collapsible boxes which hide additional information from the user. They can be added with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">details</code> liquid tag:</p> <details><summary>Click here to know more</summary> <p>Additional details, where math \(2x - 1\) and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">code</code> is rendered correctly.</p> </details> <hr/> <h2 id="layouts">Layouts</h2> <p>The main text column is referred to as the body. It is the assumed layout of any direct descendants of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">d-article</code> element.</p> <div class="fake-img l-body"> <p>.l-body</p> </div> <p>For images you want to display a little larger, try <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.l-page</code>:</p> <div class="fake-img l-page"> <p>.l-page</p> </div> <p>All of these have an outset variant if you want to poke out from the body text a little bit. For instance:</p> <div class="fake-img l-body-outset"> <p>.l-body-outset</p> </div> <div class="fake-img l-page-outset"> <p>.l-page-outset</p> </div> <p>Occasionally you’ll want to use the full browser width. For this, use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.l-screen</code>. You can also inset the element a little from the edge of the browser by using the inset variant.</p> <div class="fake-img l-screen"> <p>.l-screen</p> </div> <div class="fake-img l-screen-inset"> <p>.l-screen-inset</p> </div> <p>The final layout is for marginalia, asides, and footnotes. It does not interrupt the normal flow of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.l-body</code> sized text except on mobile screen sizes.</p> <div class="fake-img l-gutter"> <p>.l-gutter</p> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="other-typography">Other Typography?</h2> <p>Emphasis, aka italics, with <em>asterisks</em> (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">*asterisks*</code>) or <em>underscores</em> (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_underscores_</code>).</p> <p>Strong emphasis, aka bold, with <strong>asterisks</strong> or <strong>underscores</strong>.</p> <p>Combined emphasis with <strong>asterisks and <em>underscores</em></strong>.</p> <p>Strikethrough uses two tildes. <del>Scratch this.</del></p> <ol> <li>First ordered list item</li> <li>Another item ⋅⋅* Unordered sub-list.</li> <li>Actual numbers don’t matter, just that it’s a number ⋅⋅1. Ordered sub-list</li> <li>And another item.</li> </ol> <p>⋅⋅⋅You can have properly indented paragraphs within list items. Notice the blank line above, and the leading spaces (at least one, but we’ll use three here to also align the raw Markdown).</p> <p>⋅⋅⋅To have a line break without a paragraph, you will need to use two trailing spaces.⋅⋅ ⋅⋅⋅Note that this line is separate, but within the same paragraph.⋅⋅ ⋅⋅⋅(This is contrary to the typical GFM line break behaviour, where trailing spaces are not required.)</p> <ul> <li>Unordered list can use asterisks</li> <li>Or minuses</li> <li>Or pluses</li> </ul> <p><a href="https://www.google.com">I’m an inline-style link</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.google.com" title="Google's Homepage">I’m an inline-style link with title</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.mozilla.org">I’m a reference-style link</a></p> <p><a href="../blob/master/LICENSE">I’m a relative reference to a repository file</a></p> <p><a href="http://slashdot.org">You can use numbers for reference-style link definitions</a></p> <p>Or leave it empty and use the <a href="http://www.reddit.com">link text itself</a>.</p> <p>URLs and URLs in angle brackets will automatically get turned into links. http://www.example.com or <a href="http://www.example.com">http://www.example.com</a> and sometimes example.com (but not on Github, for example).</p> <p>Some text to show that the reference links can follow later.</p> <p>Here’s our logo (hover to see the title text):</p> <p>Inline-style: <img src="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/raw/master/src/common/images/icon48.png" alt="alt text" title="Logo Title Text 1"/></p> <p>Reference-style: <img src="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/raw/master/src/common/images/icon48.png" alt="alt text" title="Logo Title Text 2"/></p> <p>Inline <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">code</code> has <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">back-ticks around</code> it.</p> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">JavaScript syntax highlighting</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="nf">alert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Python syntax highlighting</span><span class="sh">"</span>
<span class="k">print</span> <span class="n">s</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>No language indicated, so no syntax highlighting.
But let's throw in a &lt;b&gt;tag&lt;/b&gt;.
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Colons can be used to align columns.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Tables</th> <th style="text-align: center">Are</th> <th style="text-align: right">Cool</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>col 3 is</td> <td style="text-align: center">right-aligned</td> <td style="text-align: right">$1600</td> </tr> <tr> <td>col 2 is</td> <td style="text-align: center">centered</td> <td style="text-align: right">$12</td> </tr> <tr> <td>zebra stripes</td> <td style="text-align: center">are neat</td> <td style="text-align: right">$1</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>There must be at least 3 dashes separating each header cell. The outer pipes (|) are optional, and you don’t need to make the raw Markdown line up prettily. You can also use inline Markdown.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Markdown</th> <th>Less</th> <th>Pretty</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><em>Still</em></td> <td><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">renders</code></td> <td><strong>nicely</strong></td> </tr> <tr> <td>1</td> <td>2</td> <td>3</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote> <p>Blockquotes are very handy in email to emulate reply text. This line is part of the same quote.</p> </blockquote> <p>Quote break.</p> <blockquote> <p>This is a very long line that will still be quoted properly when it wraps. Oh boy let’s keep writing to make sure this is long enough to actually wrap for everyone. Oh, you can <em>put</em> <strong>Markdown</strong> into a blockquote.</p> </blockquote> <p>Here’s a line for us to start with.</p> <p>This line is separated from the one above by two newlines, so it will be a <em>separate paragraph</em>.</p> <p>This line is also a separate paragraph, but… This line is only separated by a single newline, so it’s a separate line in the <em>same paragraph</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Albert Einstein</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a distill-style blog post and main elements]]></summary></entry></feed>